Guide to the Jesse Pyrant Andrews photographs and oral histories, 1973-2020 RL.00043
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Jesse Pyrant Andrews photographs and oral histories
1973-2020
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Andrews, Jesse Pyrant
RL.00043
10.2 Linear Feet 16 boxes 257 prints; 79 CD-ROMs
38.8 Gigabytes 158 audio files 79 .wav format files (35.6 gigabytes); 79 .mp3 format use copy files (3.2 gigabytes)
Jesse Pyrant Andrews (b. 1949) is an American photographer based in rural southern Virginia. Collection comprises 257 black-and-white photographs and 39 oral interviews by Jesse Pyrant Andrews documenting rural and small-town life in the Piedmont plateau of central southern Virginia and northern North Carolina. Major themes center on the landscapes and people of the region; tobacco cultivation; the lives of farmers, war veterans and laid-off workers; local architecture and historic sites; traditional crafts and music; and new patterns of economics and society in rural Virginia. The materials also include a Vietnam War veterans manuscript memoir and numerous oral histories of veterans. Additional projects include documentary narrative about the southern Virginia Carter-Wooding families; views from an Amtrak train; and street scenes and portraits taken in New York City, California, and Massachusetts. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Original negative identifiers and titles assigned by the photographer have been retained. The original identifier on the back of each print typically comprises codes for the body of work, negative file, and negative number. There are a few unnumbered prints. In the case of untitled works, descriptions in brackets have been supplied by library staff. Each print also has been given a Rubenstein Library identifier. Most of the photographs were printed by Andrews in his darkroom from the early 2000s to 2020.
Arrangement
Arranged in the following series: 13-Month Crop: One Year in the Life of a Piedmont Virginia Tobacco Farm; Bill Davis and Davis Family; Portraits; Virginia; Train Project, View from Amtrak Northeast Regional; Burlington Mills; and Life at Large and Other Work. There is also a series for original media.
Biographical Note
Documentary photographer and oral historian Jesse Pyrant Andrews (b. 1949) has photographed the changing rural landscapes of Virginia and North Carolina and the lives of its inhabitants since the mid 1970s. His documentary projects include in-depth oral history interviews that provide an important context for his portraits of Virginia veterans, farmers, immigrants, and former textile mill workers. Andrews studied at the New England School of Photography in Boston, Massachusetts, working primarily with photographers Olive Pierce and George Dewolfe. He shoots 35mm black-and-white film which he prints in his traditional darkroom.
Access Restrictions
Collection is partially restricted.
Original audiovisual media are closed to use; digital copies are available and can only be accessed onsite in the Rubenstein Library Reading Room. To request access, please contact Research Services before coming to use these records.
Provenance
The Jesse Pyrant Andrews photographs and oral histories were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as purchases from 2003 to 2020.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Digital oral history use copy files were derived from optical discs and consist of audio files in .wav (preservation copies) and .mp3 format (use copies).
Collection Overview
Collection comprises 257 black-and-white photographs and 39 oral interview recordings by Jesse Pyrant Andrews documenting rural and small-town life in the Piedmont plateau of central southern Virginia and northern North Carolina. Most of the images are portraits of farming families, immigrant workers, former textile workers, war veterans, musicians, and other local people, with scenes from homesteads, small towns, farms, and grave sites. Major themes include tobacco cultivation; the lives of war veterans and laid-off workers; regional architecture and historic sites; and traditional activities such as music-making, making handmade firearms, and working with leather. Together, the images and interviews speak to enormous changes in this rural Piedmont region as it transitions into the 21st century.
Three bodies of work whose images are found in the Portraits and Virginia series are referred to by Andrews as the Veterans, Vietnam, and Carter-Wooding Projects. The first two document the lives and struggles of U.S. veterans of World War II and the Vietnam and Gulf wars, and includes many audio interviews. The second project, also accompanied by several oral histories, documents two Halifax County, Virginia families, the Carters and Woodings, and their rural property which dates back to an 18th-century Huguenot land grant. The materials also include a Vietnam War manuscript memoir.
Additional photo projects in the collection document the lives of former textile workers (also accompanied by oral histories); a trip on an Amtrak train; and street life and people in New York City, California, and Massachusetts.
Most of the photographs are accompanied by captions written by the photographer, commenting on the individuals, their life experiences, and aspects of local culture and society.
Photographs from the series documenting tobacco farming, "13-Month Crop," were selected for a 2002 exhibit of Andrews' work hosted by the Rubenstein Library at Duke University.
A large selection of photographs in this collection has been digitized and is available online as part of the Duke Digital Collections.
Agricultural laborers -- Photographs; Agriculture -- Virginia -- Photographs; Country life -- Virginia -- Photographs; Documentary photographers -- Virginia; Documentary Photography -- United States; Farm life -- Virginia; Farms -- Virginia -- Photographs; Folk musicians -- Portraits; Medicine, Military -- Personal narratives; Portrait photography -- United States; Railroad travel -- United States -- Photographs; Textile industry -- Virginia; Textile workers -- Social conditions; Tobacco farmers -- Virginia -- Pittsylvania County -- Photographs; Tobacco industry -- Virginia -- Pittsylvania County; Veterans -- Southern States -- Personal narratives; Veterans -- United States -- Portraits; Veterans -- United States -- Social conditions -- 20th century; Vietnam War, 1961-1975 -- Personal narratives, American; Halifax County (Va.) -- History; North Carolina -- Photographs; Pittsylvania County (Va.) -- History; Southern States -- Rural conditions; Virginia -- Economic conditions; Virginia -- History; Virginia -- Photographs; Black-and-white photographs; CD-ROMs; Digital audio formats; Gelatin silver prints; Oral histories (document genre); Sound recordings; Andrews, Jesse Pyrant; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University); Burlington Industries, Inc. -- History; Davis family (Va.); Burlington Mills Corporation; Amtrak
- 13-Month Crop: One Year in the Life of a Piedmont Virginia Tobacco Farm, 2000-2001; 1.5 Linear Feet 38 prints
  Scope and Contents note
  Series contains 38 11x14 inch black-and-white (gelatin silver) prints exhibited at Duke University's Perkins Library, August 7-December 14, 2002. Andrews spent one tobacco farming season, April 2000 to April 2001, using a traditional film camera to document the lives of the people who were involved in cultivating tobacco on the Moore family farm in Pittsylvania County, Virginia. Images portray the white farm family members as well as migrant Latino farmworkers. Tobacco farming is such labor-intensive work that it is often called a "13-month crop."
  - Charles Moore and Terry Moore preparing land for planting, early spring 2000 (Box 1, Image RL00043_P_001)
    Orig. print number: JA/13MCA 1-34
  - Lillian Moore at the Moore homeplace, 2000 (Box 1, Image RL00043_P_002)
    Orig. print number: JA/13MCA 1-20
  - Terry and his daughter Christine during a break from seeding greenhouse trays, early spring 2001 (Box 1, Image RL00043_P_003)
    Orig. print number: JA/13MCA 5-33
  - Christine helping with the seeding of the greenhouse trays, early spring 2001 (Box 1, Image RL00043_P_004)
    Orig. print number: JA/13MCA 6-19
  - Roy Younger placing seeded trays in the greenhouse bed, early spring 2001 (Box 1, Image RL00043_P_005)
    Orig. print number: JA/13MCA 3-24A-25
  - Terry with a tray of seedlings ready for planting, spring 2000 (Box 1, Image RL00043_P_006)
    Orig. print number: JA/13MCA 3-18A-19
  - Loading the planter on the first day of planting, spring 2000 (Box 1, Image RL00043_P_007)
    Orig. print number: JA/13MCA 3-9
  - First day of planting, spring 2000 (Box 1, Image RL00043_P_008)
    Orig. print number: JA/13MCA 1-10
  - Planting, spring 2000 (Box 1, Image RL00043_P_009)
    Orig. print number: JA/13MCA 1-22A
  - Eduardo Pineda Arzata, who has worked at the Moore farm for twelve years, at the curing barns, summer 2000 (Box 1, Image RL00043_P_010)
    Orig. print number: JA/13MCA 4-2
  - Leonel Perez Gutierrez, who has worked at the Moore farm for four years, summer 2000 (Box 1, Image RL00043_P_011)
    Orig. print number: JA/13MCA 4-11
  - Maximo Perez Gutierrez, who has worked at the Moore farm for nine years, summer 2000 (Box 1, Image RL00043_P_012)
    Orig. print number: JA/13MCA 4-8
  - Eduardo Pineda Arzata cultivating by hand, spring 2000 (Box 1, Image RL00043_P_013)
    Orig. print number: JA/13MCA 5-24
  - Cam Moore, Terry's son, cultivating young tobacco, late spring 2000 (Box 1, Image RL00043_P_014)
    Orig. print number: JA/13MCA 5-29A-30
  - Terry in the final step of cultivation known as "laying by," late spring 2000 (Box 1, Image RL00043_P_015)
    Orig. print number: JA/13MCA 6-32
  - Christine Moore aboard Moira, and Renee, her mother, summer 2000 (Box 1, Image RL00043_P_016)
    Orig. print number: JA/13MCA 2-22
  - The Moore family gathered at the homeplace after Sunday dinner, summer 2000 (Box 1, Image RL00043_P_017)
    Orig. print number: JA/13MCA 6-5
  - Terry and workers, from left to right, Leonel, Eduardo and Maximo spraying to control tobacco stalk shoots called suckers, summer 2000 (Box 1, Image RL00043_P_018)
    Orig. print number: JA/13MCA 2-29A-30
  - Eduardo "topping" the flowered plants, summer 2000 (Box 1, Image RL00043_P_019)
    Orig. print number: JA/13MCA 6-24
  - Irrigating, summer 2000 (Box 1, Image RL00043_P_020)
    Orig. print number: JA/13MCA 2-33
  - Terry inspecting for suckers, summer 2000 (Box 2, Image RL00043_P_021)
    Orig. print number: JA/13MCA 1-6
  - "Pulling" or harvesting the top leaves near the season's end, summer 2000 (Box 2, Image RL00043_P_022)
    Orig. print number: JA/13MCA 2-9A-10
  - Charles Moore and workers with the final trailer of tobacco of the season, late summer 2000 (Box 2, Image RL00043_P_023)
    Orig. print number: JA/13MCA 5-36
  - Early morning, Terry sweeping out an empty barn, summer 2000 (Box 2, Image RL00043_P_024)
    Orig. print number: JA/13MCA 3-22
  - Betty Starlin, Terry, and Eduardo Pineda taking a break from barning, summer 2000 (Box 2, Image RL00043_P_025)
    Orig. print number: JA/13MCA 1-31
  - Pro-tobacco poster at Holland's Warehouse, late summer 2000 (Box 2, Image RL00043_P_026)
    Orig. print number: JA/13MCA 6-26
  - Terry with cousins Caleb and George Moore at their farm, summer 2000 (Box 2, Image RL00043_P_027)
    Orig. print number: JA/13MCA 5-6
  - Leonel Perez baling cured tobacco early morning, summer 2000 (Box 2, Image RL00043_P_028)
    Orig. print number: JA/13MCA 6-22
  - Betty and Eduardo barning newly pulled leaves, summer 2000 (Box 2, Image RL00043_P_029)
    Orig. print number: JA/13MCA 2-32
  - Terry and Leonel sheeting cured leaves from the barns, summer 2000 (Box 2, Image RL00043_P_030)
    Orig. print number: JA/13MCA 3-28
  - Sheeting tobacco at Caleb and George's farm, summer 2000 (Box 2, Image RL00043_P_031)
    Orig. print number: JA/13MCA 1-30
  - Eduardo, Leonel, and Maximo pushing an 850-pound bale of tobacco onto the loader in preparation for market, summer 2000 (Box 2, Image RL00043_P_032)
    Orig. print number: JA/13MCA 2-19
  - Terry and Charles at Holland's Warehouse on the first day of the market, Danville, Virginia, summer 2000 (Box 2, Image RL00043_P_033)
    Orig. print number: JA/13MCA 1-36
  - Terry with Dan and Danny Robertson, Owners of Holland's Warehouse, Danville, Va., summer 2000 (Box 2, Image RL00043_P_034)
    Orig. print number: JA/13MCA 5-30
  - A tobacco auction in progress, Holland's Warehouse, Danville, Virginia, late summer 2000 (Box 2, Image RL00043_P_035)
    Orig. print number: JA/13MCA 5-20
  - Terry receiving his check for tobacco sales, Holland's Warehouse, Danville, Virginia, late summer 2000 (Box 2, Image RL00043_P_036)
    Orig. print number: JA/13MCA 6-25
  - Terry sows wheat as a cover crop, fall 2000 (Box 2, Image RL00043_P_037)
    Orig. print number: JA/13MCA 3-36
  - Terry Moore in his firefighter's gear, 2001 May (Box 5, Image RL00043_P_119)
    Orig. print number: JA/13MCB 109-XX
- Bill Davis and Davis family, 1976-2006 and undated; .5 Linear Feet 18 prints
  Series is made up of 18 11x14 inch black-and-white (gelatin silver) photographs, the majority of which feature portraits of Bill and Nat Davis, brothers from an established rural family from the Piedmont plateau region of Pittsylvania County in south-central Virginia. Images range from the landscapes and sites around this family farm to the portraits of the two brothers Bill and Nat. One includes a sister, Nancy Paige Davis. There are several images of Bill's burial and gravesite.
  - William Arastus Davis (Bill), 1988 (Box 2, Image RL00043_P_038)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 4x5-1
  - Bill Davis braiding a belt from deer hide, 1988 (Box 2, Image RL00043_P_039)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 88-20
    Bill learned to braid leather when he was a child. His father did not want him to learn that craft so he would take the strands of leather under the covers of his bed at night and practice braiding simply by feel. He could do any sort of braid from the most simple to making what he called a "rosette," a round knot woven from 16 strands of leather, seemingly with no beginning or end.
  - Bill Davis playing a chromatic harmonica, 1988 (Box 2, Image RL00043_P_040)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 45-26A
    The chair he is sitting in was made by his grandfather, Simeon Benton Davis.
  - Bill Davis with his younger sister, Nancy Paige Davis, 1990 (Box 2, Image RL00043_P_041)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 43-16A
    Bill was much older than Nancy. When she turned 18, she wanted to attend the nursing school at the University of Virginia, but their father refused to pay for her to go. Bill eventually saved enough money to send her and she graduated in 1941. She never returned to the farm except to visit and lived in Richmond until her death in 2005. This image was made during her last visit to see Bill. She always referred to him as her angel and thus she was making a halo for him.
  - Orbrey Nathaniel Davis (Nat), 1979 (Box 2, Image RL00043_P_042)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 88-38
    Nat had been telling me about one of his first girlfriends. He was sad because he thought no one would ever care for him again.
  - Bill and Nat Davis playing music on their front porch, 1978 (Box 2, Image RL00043_P_043)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 42-27
    They knew hundreds of old time tunes as well as hymns and ballads.
  - Bill Davis grave, 2006 November (Box 2, Image RL00043_P_044)
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 12-XX
  - The Davis family cemetery, 2006 (Box 2, Image RL00043_P_045)
  - All that is left of what Nat Davis referred to as the "big woods," undated (Box 2, Image RL00043_P_046)
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 14-XX
    This is where Hat and Bill hunted and trapped their entire lives. Bill used to say that the mound in the background was an Indian burial place.
  - Site of the Davis family spring, 2006 November (Box 2, Image RL00043_P_047)
    This spring was where they got their water for nearly 100 years. It is now a mosquito breeding ground.
  - Site of the Davis family homeplace, 2006 November (Box 3, Image RL00043_P_048)
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 13-XX
  - William Arastus Davis (Bill Davis), 1900-1991, on the Davis Farm near Chatham, Virginia, 1976 (Box 3, Image RL00043_P_049)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 84-43
    Bill was a friend of my grandmother. When I was a child, she would take me with her to visit the Davis farm. I knew the Davises very well. They are all dead now, their farm sold and is now a high-end housing development. The Davis family was a real link to the past. They never got accustomed to the Twentieth Century.
  - Bill Davis, 1989 November (Box 3, Image RL00043_P_050)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 42-24
    Bill had gotten out his wool army uniform for cold weather.
  - Bill Davis's burial, 1991 August (Box 3, Image RL00043_P_051)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 51-12A
    Pictured are (from left) Calvin Daniel, Ricky Adkins, and Dennis Daniel. Calvin Daniel inherited the Davis farm. These men dug Bill's grave. They and I were the only people at the burial. Bill asked me to make this last image of him at the family cemetery.
  - Orbrey Nathaniel Davis (Nat Davis), 1898-1987, at Davis farm, 1978 October (Box 3, Image RL00043_P_052)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 88-39
    This is Bill Davis' brother.
  - Nat Davis skinning foxes, 1984 November (Box 3, Image RL00043_P_053)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 56-8ND
    This was Nat's primary source of income. Occasionally he would trap a mink. Nat was also an avid turkey hunter.
  - Bill Davis on his birthday, 1989 May 21 (Box 3, Image RL00043_P_054)
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 80-15
  - Bill Davis fleshing out a deer hide, Chatham, Virginia, 1982 (Box 3, Image RL00043_P_055)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 45-30
    Bill would tan fresh deer hides to use in his leather work. He made a device which would split a hide into evenly sized strips for braiding. He made belts, sashes, hat bands, watch fobs, key holders, and guitar straps. He also did harness repairs and remade worn out shoes. But the first step in this process was to pick all the flesh off the hide. If left, the bits of flesh would attract insects to eat the hide and leave uncured spots on the finished hide.
- Portraits, 1975-2019; 2.2 Linear Feet 48 photographic prints; 48 CD-ROMs; 1 notebook; 22.7 Gigabytes 96 files 48 .wav files; 48 .mp3 files
  Series consists of 48 11x14 inch black-and-white portraits of individuals taken by photographer Jesse Pyrant Andrews in Virginia and North Carolina, with a few from Tennessee and California. Subjects include men and women, teenagers, and fathers and mothers with their sons, chiefly from rural areas and small towns. The series includes portraits of war veterans who served in World War II, Vietnam, and the Iraq War, and which form part of Andrews' Veterans Project (also incorporating his Vietnam Project). These portraits have accompanying biographical captions and oral history recordings. The portrait of Vietnam veteran Donald Wright is also accompanied by Wright's handwritten journal describing events in Vietnam and after the war.
  As portraiture is one of the photographer's favored formats, additional portraits - sometimes of the same people in this Portraits series - are found in other project series.
  Titles and original negative identifiers assigned by the photographer have been retained. Prints in this series are arranged in order as received.
  Conditions Governing Access
  The oral histories accompanying the prints are open to research use. As they require additional preparation time for access, please contact the Rubenstein Library before coming to use this materials.
  - Mark Aaron, Esmont, Virginia, 2003 (Box 3, Image RL00043_P_132)
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 65-8
  - Mark Aaron, Callands, Virginia, 2001 (Box 3, Image RL00043_P_133)
    Scope and Contents
    Orig. print number: JA/LAL 147-9
  - Stewart Werner and his son Stewart Werner Jr., Halifax, Virginia, 2007 (Box 3, Image RL00043_P_134)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 116-6
  - Rud Shupik, Callands, Virginia, 2002 (Box 3, Image RL00043_P_135)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 57-14
  - Rud Shupik, Riceville, Virginia, 2001 (Box 3, Image RL00043_P_136)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 2-15
  - Moira Riser, Pelham, North Carolina, 2003 (Box 3, Image RL00043_P_137)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 4-3
  - John Riser, Pelham, North Carolina, 2003 (Box 3, Image RL00043_P_138)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 14-7
  - Rachael Martin, Halifax, Virginia, 2008 (Box 3, Image RL00043_P_139)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 123-8
  - Giles Motley, Pittsylvania County, Virginia, 1998 (Box 3, Image RL00043_P_140)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 41-14
  - Watermelon vendor, Tightsqueeze, Virginia, 1992 (Box 3, Image RL00043_P_141)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 86-27
  - Richard Stoner and his mother, Beatrice Stoner, 2004 (Box 3, Image RL00043_P_142)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 106-12
  - Jerry Smith and his mother, Norma Smith, 2003 (Box 3, Image RL00043_P_143)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 4x5-9
  - David Crowder, near Crossville, Tennessee, 1977 August (Box 5, Image RL00043_P_115)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 40-33
    He picked me up hitchhiking.
  - Fox and Willie May Hold, near Crossville, Tennessee, 1977 August (Box 5, Image RL00043_P_116)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 40-13
  - Crystal Graber, Ontario, California, 1992 (Box 5, Image RL00043_P_117)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 88-21_A
  - Helen Marshall at Forest Home, Blanch, North Carolina, 1997 (Box 5, Image RL00043_P_118)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 4x5-24
  - Holly Hernandsen, Pelham, North Carolina, 2002 October (Box 5, Image RL00043_P_120)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 3-49
  - Dirk and Jack, Marshall, Virginia, 1977 June (Box 7, Image RL00043_P_150)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 42-44
  - Sadie Conklin, Ontario, California, 1977 August (Box 7, Image RL00043_P_151)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 63-7
    Ms. Conklin was born in 1884 in Conklin, California, where she lived her entire life. Her father "came to California in a covered wagon." Regrettably I have made no recordings of her.
  - Joe Thompson at home, Mebane, North Carolina, 2003 (Box 10, Image RL00043_P_194)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 104-9
    Born in 1919, Joe Thompson was the last of his generation to play American "old time" music, in a style which evolved among black musicians in the rural South as far back as the antebellum years. Joe's playing had a unique sound and rhythm, shaped by his association with older musicians in his childhood and by continuing to play with other black "old time" musicians throughout his life. His cousin Odell played banjo with him until his death. Joe Thompson was a veteran of WWII. Trained as a bulldozer operator, he told me that he "built roads and buried bodies from Normandy to Berlin." He worked in the former White Furniture factory in Mebane until his retirement. He died in 2012.
  - Gary Lynch, Franklin County, Virginia, 2018 January 7; 3 items 1 print; 2 CDs (Box 12, Image RL00043_P_203, Digital-materials RL.00043-SET-0001u, Audio-file RL00043-CD-0041.MP3, Audio-file RL00043-CD-0042.MP3)
    Orig. print number: JA/POR 172-16
    Gary Lynch grew up hard on a Franklin County tobacco farm. His father made white liquor and was in and out of jail. Gary was very much influenced by his grandomther, who taught him to love gardening and famring. He later earned a BS in horticulture and has been very successful with that career. Oral history accompanies this print.
    The oral history is open to research use. As it requires advance preparation for use, please contact the Rubenstein Library before coming to use this material.